<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speech of Sr. Edward Turner Kt speaker of the honourable House of Commons, to the King's Most Excellent Majesty, delivered on Fryday the twentieth day of December, 1661.</title>
            <title>Speech of Sir Edward Turner, Kt.</title>
            <author>Turnor, Edward, Sir, 1617-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3353</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221817</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833071</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833071</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37546</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37546)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2158:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speech of Sr. Edward Turner Kt speaker of the honourable House of Commons, to the King's Most Excellent Majesty, delivered on Fryday the twentieth day of December, 1661.</title>
                  <title>Speech of Sir Edward Turner, Kt.</title>
                  <author>Turnor, Edward, Sir, 1617-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Williams at the sign of the Crown in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: The speech of Sir Edward Turner, Kt.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37546:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:37546:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <p>THE SPEECH OF Sr. EDWARD TURNER Kt. <hi>Speaker of the honourable Houſe of Commons, to the KING'S moſt excellent Majeſty, delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on Fryday the twentieth day of December,</hi> 1661.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for JOHN WILLIAMS at the ſign of the <hi>Crown</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1662.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37546:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37546:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your moſt excellent Majeſty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He laſt time the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes of the Commons Houſe of Parliament had the honour to waite upon you in this place, your Majeſtie was graciouſly pleaſed to congratulate with them for the glorious meeting of the Lords ſpiritual and temporal, and Commons of <hi>England,</hi> in this your full, free, and legal Parliament.</p>
            <p>Great Sir, it is our preſent comfort, and will be our future glory, that God hath made us inſtrumental for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairs of thoſe breaches, which the worſt of times had made upon the beſt of Governments. The late great <hi>Eclipſe</hi> in our <hi>Horizon,</hi> occaſioned by the interpoſition of the earth, is now vaniſhed; the ſtars in our Firmament are now full of light; the light of our Moon is become like the light of the Sun; and the light of our Sun is ſevenfold.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37546:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
A man that ſees the River of <hi>Thames</hi> at a high water, &amp; obſerves how much it ſinks in a few hours, would think it running quite away, but by the ſecret providence of God, we ſee that when the ebbe is at the loweſt, the tyde of a riſing water is neareſt the return.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſtie was likewiſe graciouſly pleaſed to ſpeak ſomething to us on Your own behalf; and did vouchſafe to ſay you would ask ſomething for your ſelf; withall, declaring ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſineſſe in your condition, by reaſon of ſome crying debts which daily called for ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Great Sir, I am not able to expreſſe, at the hearing of thoſe words, with what a Sympathy the whole body of the Parliamen was preſently affected; The circulation of the bloud, of which our late naturaliſts do tell us, was never ſo ſenſibly demonſtrated, as by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment; before your Majeſties words were all fallen from your lips, you might have ſeen us bluſh; all our bloud came into our faces, from thence it haſted down without obſtruction to every part of the body, and after a due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting of the ſeveral parts, it was found neceſſary to breathe a vein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37546:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
We cannot forget how much our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hath been exhauſted, but we remember alſo, 'twas by Uſurping and Tyrannical powers; and therefore we are eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to be at ſome more expence to keep them out.</p>
            <p>The Merchant tels us, 'tis good pollicy in a troubled Sea to loſe ſome part of our <hi>Cargoe,</hi> thereby to ſave the reſt.</p>
            <p>With Your Majeſty's leave, we have been bold to look into the preſent ſtate of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and find thoſe great ſums that have been heretofore advanced upon us, were raiſed moſt of them in bad Times, and for ill purpoſes, to keep Your Majeſty out of this Your Native Kingdom: And when Your Majeſty returned home from Your long baniſhment, you found the Naval Store houſe unfurniſh'd, which will not eaſily be ſupplyed: The unſetled humors, and unquiet Spirits that are yet amongſt us, do neceſsitate a Coſtly Guard for your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Perſon: The honorable Acceſſions of <hi>Dunkirk, Tangier</hi> and <hi>Jamaica</hi> do at preſent <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
